Guide to the New Mine Sapphire Syndicate Records 1889-1967
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
New Mine Sapphire Syndicate Records
1889-1967
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 028
New Mine Sapphire Syndicate
5 linear feet 10 boxes and 1 oversize box
The New Mine Sapphire Syndicate mined sapphires in Utica, Montana, in Judith Basin County. The collection contains the company's governing documents, financial records, correspondence, legal documents and court papers, reports, clippings, publicity and printed materials, and photographs.
Historical Note
Originally discovered by prospectors in search of placer gold, the rich sapphire-bearing ledge of Montana was located and claimed by three Montanans in 1896. The New Mine Sapphire Syndicate, based solely on the Yogo Sapphire District near Utica, Montana, in Judith Basin County, was incorporated in 1898. S.S. Hobson served as vice president, and Mathew Dunn and George A. Wells, both Great Falls residents, served respectively as president and secretary-treasurer. Soon after the turn of the century, the corporation came under the control of British investors and was to remain so until 1949. The Yogo mines operated profitably until 1927, when a flash flood destroyed the surface workings of the Syndicate's operation. After that, little was done to exploit the remaining sapphires. In 1956, Thomas Sidwell succeeded in purchasing the controlling interest in the Syndicate. Lack of capital hampered his operations until 1956-1957, when the Syndicate's stock was re-issued and some work resumed at the mine. Law suits, prior claims, poor management, and bad luck combined to ruin the renewed operations of the corporation, and the venture was bankrupt by 1961.
The collection contains the company's governing documents, financial records, correspondence, legal documents and court papers, reports, clippings, publicity and printed materials, and photographs.
The collection is arranged in ten series:
Series I: Governance and History, 4 folders, 1898-1960
Series II: Correspondence, 1 linear foot, 1898-1963
Series III: Financial Records, 3 linear feet, 1909-1960
Series IV: Court Papers, 4 folders, 1956-1960
Series V: Legal Documents, 4 folders, 1889-1967
Series VI: Reports, 1 folder, 1910-1959
Series VII: Maps and Blueprints, 1 folder, undated
Series VIII: Clippings, 1 folder, 1950-1960
Series IX: Publicity, 2 folders, 1950-1960
Series X: Photographs, 22 items, 1924-1925
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and the University of Montana-Missoula.
The records were in the possession of John Wight and Marvel Lowrance, owners of the Syndicate's assets, until time of donation.
Gift of Marvel Lowrance and John Wight, 1970.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Investments, British--Montana--Yogo Creek Region; Mining corporations--Montana--Yogo Creek Region; Sapphire mines and mining--Montana--Yogo Creek Region
Business records--Montana--Yogo Creek Region
Montana; Business, Industry, and Labor; Mines and Mineral Resources
- Governance and History, 1898-1960; Series I; 4 folders
  This series contains documentation on the governance and history of the company. It includes corporate histories written within and without the company, founding documents (articles of incorporation, resolutions), and some minutes of Board of Directors meetings, mostly from the earliest years of the company.
  - Company history, 1956 and undated (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Organization, 1898-1948 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Organization, 1948-1962 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1898-1960 (Box-folder 1/4)
- Correspondence, 1898-1963; Series II; 1 linear foot
  This series contains incoming and outgoing correspondence from the company.
  - Correspondence, 1898-1899 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Correspondence, 1910-1914 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Correspondence, 1918-1923 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Correspondence, 1924-1927 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Correspondence, 1928-1931 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Correspondence, 1932-1939 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Correspondence, 1945-1951 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Correspondence, 1952-1953 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Correspondence, 1956 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Correspondence, January-September, 1957 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Correspondence, October-December, 1957 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Correspondence, January-March, 1958 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Correspondence, April-June, 1958 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Correspondence, July-December, 1958 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Correspondence, January-March, 1959 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Correspondence, April-June, 1959 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Correspondence, July-September, 1959 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Correspondence, October-December, 1959 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Correspondence, 1962 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Correspondence, 1963 (Box-folder 3/4)
- Financial Records, 1909-1960; Series III; 3 linear feet
  This series contains the company's financial records, including those related to taxes, stockholders, unemployment compensation, operating statements, general ledgers, check stubs, ledgers, and journals. There are also some of Thomas Sidwell's personal financial materials.
  - Employer's Federal tax returns, 1957-1961 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - U.S. Corporation Income Tax Returns, 1909-1930 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - U.S. Corporation Income Tax Returns, 1952-1959 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - U.S. Income Tax return (Sidwell), 1959 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Montana State Income Tax, 1957-1960 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Montana State Income Tax return (Sidwell), 1959 (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Montana Corporation License Tax, 1921-1930 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Montana Corporation License Tax, 1956-1959 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Montana Net Proceeds Tax, 1903-1930 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Montana Net Proceeds Tax, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 3/14)
  - Unemployment Compensation Reports, 1957-1960 (Box-folder 3/15)
  - Judith Basin County Real Estate Tax, 1956-1961 (Box-folder 3/16)
  - Annual Report to the Secretary of State of Montana, 1956-1961 (Box-folder 3/17)
  - Annual Reports, 1898-1929 (Box-folder 3/18)
  - Stockholders' list, 1938 (Box-folder 3/19)
  - Stockholders' list, 1957-1965 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Stock Certificates Book, 1959-1967 (Box-volume 11OS/7)
  - Register of Shares, 1914-1949 (Box-volume 4/1)
  - Cancelled stock certificates, undated (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Cancelled stock certificates, undated (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Stock sales, prospect lists, undated (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Stock subscriptions and sales records, undated (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Stock transfers, 1957-1960 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - Stock releases, 1967 (Box-folder 5/3)
  - New Mine properties and titles, undated (Box-folder 5/4)
  - General ledger, 1914-1936 (Box-volume 5/2)
  - General ledger, 1958-1960 (Box-volume 6/3)
  - General ledger, 1955-1958 (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Sapphire Stock inventories, 1922-1933 (Box-folder 6/2)
  - Accounts payable, 1957-1960 (Box-folder 6/3)
  - Payroll withholding statements, 1957 (Box-folder 6/4)
  - Trial balances, 1911-1912 (Box-folder 6/5)
  - Financial statements, 1957-1960 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - Operating statements, 1919-1932 (Box-folder 6/7)
  - Operating statements, 1955-1960 (Box-folder 6/8)
  - Check stubs, 1956-1959 (Box-folder 6/9)
  - Check stubs, 1959-1960 (Box-volume 7/8)
  - Check stubs, 1959-1960 (Box-volume 7/9)
  - Miscellaneous, 1909-1938 (Box-folder 7/1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1957-1960 (Box-folder 7/2)
  - Journal, 1931-1949 (Box-volume 7/1)
  - Private ledger, 1922-1953 (Box-volume 8/4)
  - Cash book, 1911-1936 (Box-volume 8/5)
- Court Papers, 1956-1960; Series IV; 4 folders
  This series contains court papers related to a 1956-1960 case, Gadsden vs. New Mine Sapphire Syndicate. At issue were Gadsden's assets after her husband, Charles T. Gadsden (a New Sapphire manager of many years) died in 1954.
  - Maude Margaret Gadsden Vs. New Mine Sapphire Syndicate, 1956-1959 (Box-folder 8/1)
  - Maude Margaret Gadsden Vs. New Mine Sapphire Syndicate, 1956 (Box-folder 8/2)
  - Maude Margaret Gadsden vs. New Mine Sapphire Syndicate, 1956-1958 (Box-folder 9/1)
  - Maude Margaret Gadsden vs. New Mine Sapphire Syndicate, 1959-1960 (Box-folder 9/2)
- Legal Documents, 1889-1967; Series V; 4 folders
  This series contains legal documents, including deeds, patents, and materials related to the company's mining claims.
  - Deeds and Patents, 1889-1928 (Box-folder 9/3)
  - Agreements, 1896-1920 (Box-folder 9/4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1894-1944 (Box-folder 9/5)
  - Mining claims, undated (Box-folder 10/1)
  - Mining claims, undated (Box-folder 10/2)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box-folder 10/3)
- Reports, 1910-1959; Series VI; 1 folder
  This series consists of one folder of reports produced or commissioned by the New Mine Sapphire Syndicate. Most relate to mining claims.
  - Reports, 1910-1959 (Box-folder 10/4)
- Maps and Blueprints, undated; Series VII; 1 folder
  This series consists of two folders of maps and blueprints related to the operations of the New Mine Sapphire Syndicate. Some relate to mining claims, and others are unidentified.
  - Maps and Blueprints, undated (Box-folder 10/5 and OS)
- Clippings, 1950-1960; Series VIII; 1 folder
  This series contains newspaper and magazine clippings, mostly from Montana publications, about the Yogo sapphires.
  - Clippings, 1950-1960 (Box-folder 10/6)
- Publications and Publicity, 1950-1960; Series IX; 2 folders
  This series contains printed and other publicity materials produced by and for the company.
  - Publications and Publicity, 1950-1960 (Box-folder 10/7)
  - Publications and Publicity, 1950-1960 (Box-folder 11OS)
- Photographs, 1924-1925 and undated; Series X; 22 items
  This series contains photographs of the New Mine Sapphire Syndicate operation in Utica, Montana. Most were taken around 1924-1925, and show the buildings, mechanicals, and other aspects of the mine site and mining equipment. Several images show damage after floods.
  - Photographs, undated (Box-folder 10/8)
  - Workings at New Mine Sapphire Syndicate, Utica, Montana, circa 1925; 79-0002
  - Shaft house and compressor house, New Mine Sapphire Syndicate, Utica, Montana, circa 1925; 79-0003
  - Workings at New Mine Sapphire Syndicate, Utica, Montana, circa 1925; 79-0004
  - "The shaft house, old blacksmith shop, new blacksmith shop, carpenter shop, railway on left to dump, New Mine Sapphire Syndicate, Utica, Montana", circa 1925; 79-0005
  - "Dam no. 1, showing how 1-inch board heave up. 2-inch lay much better. These boards have been in since 1910, but do not rot in lower part of dam where they are wet but do heave up", 1925; 79-0006
  - "Looking down in the mine", circa 1925; 79-0007
  - "Dam no. 1", 1925; 79-0008
  - New Mine Sapphire Syndicate, Utica, Montana, circa 1925; 79-0009
  - "Dirt at old camp washed once in 1920, center cut out wider by cloudburst, 1923", 1924; 79-0010
  - "Wash rock washed [illegible] of first flood", 1924; 79-0011
  - "Pile under trestle only new dirt left", 1924; 79-0012
  - New Mine Sapphire Syndicate, Utica, Montana, circa 1925; 79-0013
  - New Mine Sapphire Syndicate, Utica, Montana, circa 1925; 79-0014
  - New Mine Sapphire Syndicate, Utica, Montana, circa 1925; 79-0015
  - New Mine Sapphire Syndicate, Utica, Montana, circa 1925; 79-0016
  - New Mine Sapphire Syndicate, Utica, Montana, circa 1925; 79-0017
  - New Mine Sapphire Syndicate, Utica, Montana, circa 1925; 79-0018
  - New Mine Sapphire Syndicate, Utica, Montana, circa 1925; 79-0019
  - Sapphires, probably from Yogo mines, near Utica, Montana, undated; 79-0020
  - "Underground workings" [probably Yogo mines], undated; 79-0021